A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 6262-9286 FA739C
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 6262-9286
1936-2005
1950s-1990s
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA739C
45.76 Cubic Feet Document boxes 281-385.
Conditions Governing Access
Catalogued Reports are open for scholarly research, with select reports restricted as noted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Other Finding Aids
For descriptions of Ford Foundation Catalogued Reports, please refer to the following finding aids (arranged by Report Number):
FA739A Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 1-3254
FA739B Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 3255-6261
FA739D Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 9287-11774
FA739E Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 11775-13948
FA739F Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 13949-17726
FA739G Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 17727-19980
Arrangement
The Catalogued Reports are arranged numerically by an arbitrary call number assigned during cataloging, from 1 to approximately 20,000.
Biographical / Historical
In the early 1970s, the Ford Foundation’s archives staff began to identify and catalog individual reports, policy and programming documents, and program evaluations in an effort to create an internal lending-library of useful documents. Many of the Catalogued Reports were physically culled from the former Foundation officers’ and staff’s archival collections of ‘office files’. When those collections of ‘office files’ were later processed, and finding aids created, an appendix of “Reports Removed” (or, Reports Transferred”) was added to the finding aids.
By 1977 the collection included more than 3,500 reports, and by 1979 some 5,000 reports had been cataloged.
Duplicated copies of the reports were also created on microfiche, and later microfilm.
Scope and Contents
The Ford Foundation’s Catalogued Reports collection includes policy and programming documents, program evaluations, and periodic program status reports produced by Foundation officers and staff, as well as consultants and grantees. Some published material produced by Ford Foundation grants is also included in the collection. The collection also includes some of the Ford Foundation’s own publications, such as the Annual Reports and newsletters.
Ford Foundation; Ford Foundation
- Special cumulative financial statement prepared for meeting of Executive Committee International Food Policy Research Institute (Reports 006262), 1977 (Box 281)
  Program Name
  International Division
  Extent
  7 p. + attachment: principally tables
  Food policy -- Developing countries; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations -- United States -- Finance; Endowments -- Developing countries; Ford Foundation. International Division; Ford Foundation
- Draft materials on expanded programs for women (Reports 006263), 1980 (Box 281)
  Abstract/Summary
  Memo to Franklin Thomas dated February 20, 1980.
  3 p. + attachments
  Women -- Services for -- Developing countries; Women -- Legal status, laws, etc.; Women's rights -- Developing countries; Women -- Employment -- Developing countries; Endowments -- Developing countries; Bell, David E., 1919-; Berresford, Susan V. (Susan Vail), 1943-; Ford Foundation. International Division
- The Ford Foundation minority fellowship programs: A midpoint review (Reports 006264), 1976 (Box 281)
  Education and Research
  39 p.: tables
  Minority students -- United States; Scholarships -- United States; Universities and colleges -- United States -- Graduate work; Education (Graduate) -- United States; Payton, Benjamin Franklin, 1932-; Ford Foundation. Education and Research
- An examination of alternative approaches to strengthening national educational research capacity in the English-speaking Caribbean 1971. (Reports 006265) (Box 281)
  International Division/Latin America and the Caribbean
  147 p.
  Education -- Research -- Caribbean, English-speaking; Education -- Research -- Caribbean Area; Education, Higher -- Caribbean, English-speaking; Education, Higher -- Caribbean Area; Teachers -- Training of -- Caribbean, English-speaking; Teachers -- Training of; Ford Foundaton. Latin America and the Caribbean
- Report on Ford Foundation "special projects" 1962. (Reports 006266) (Box 281)
  Special Programs
  11 p.: ill., principally port.
  Rural development -- Syria; Home economics -- Study and teaching -- Syria; Agriculture -- Study and teaching -- Syria; Ford Foundation. Special Programs
- University reorganization in Algeria (Reports 006267), 1974 (Box 281)
  International Division/Middle East and Africa
  2 p.
  Universities and colleges -- Algeria -- Administration; Education, Higher -- Algeria; Higher education and state -- Algeria; Education and state -- Algeria; Fox, Melvin J.; Ford Foundation. Middle East and Africa
- Ford Foundation staff visit to China: Agricultural economics and policy (Reports 006268), 1979 (Box 281)
  Ford members include: Lowell S. Hardin, Reed Hertford, Dwight H. Perkins, and Sumter L.Travers.
  International Division/Asia and the Pacific
  Agriculture -- Economic aspects -- China; Rural development -- China; Germain, Adrienne
- Report on a survey of opinion on management problems in Indonesia (Reports 006269), 1970 (Box 281)
  16 p. + attachment: forms
  Industrial management -- Indonesia; Management -- Indonesia; Public administration -- Indonesia -- Management; Executives -- Training of -- Indonesia; Joedono, Satrio Boedihardjo, 1940-; Ford Foundation. Asia and the Pacific
- Family planning and population activities in Eastern Africa: a meeting of representatives of international aid organizations, Nairobi, November 1968: summary notes. (Reports 006270) (Box 281)
  Meeting of representatives of 11 organizations interested in problems of development in Eastern Africa to discuss population and family planning activities in the region.
  8 p.
  Birth control -- Africa, Eastern
- Working papers submitted to the general board for the reorganization of the machinery of government nos. 1-4 (Reports 006271), 1982 (Box 281)
  Overseas Division/Middle East and Africa
  various pagings.
  Public administration -- Egypt -- Reorganization; Administrative agencies -- Egypt -- Reorganization; Gulick, Luther Halsey, 1892-1993; Ford Foundation. Middle East and Africa; Maʻhad al-Takhṭīṭ al-Qawmī (Egypt)
- Strengthening professional competence at selected universities (Reports 006272), 1964 (Box 281)
  Memo to Henry Heald dated February 12, 1964.
  International Training and Research
  Foreign study -- United States; Foreign study -- Developing countries; Professional education -- United States; Professional education - Developing countries; Universities and colleges -- United States -- Graduate work; Education (Graduate) -- United States; Faust, Clarence H. (Clarence Henry), 1901-1975; Ford Foundation. International Training and Research
- Nutrition in Latin America (Reports 006273), 1973 (Box 281)
  Office of Reports/International Division/Latin America and the Caribbean
  5 p.
  Birth control -- Study and teaching -- Latin America; Children -- Health and hygiene -- Latin America; Nutrition -- Latin America; Malnutrition -- Social aspects -- Latin America; Magat, Richard
- Procedures for grant development in India (Reports 006274), 1968 (Box 281)
  Outline of procedures for the development of new grant programs in India.
  International Division/Asia and the Pacific;India, Nepal and Sri Lanka
  21 leaves
  Charity organization -- India; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations -- United States -- Finance; Philanthropy -- India; Kennedy, J. P. (John Patrick), 1930-; Ford Foundation India; Ford Foundation. Asia and the Pacific; Ford Foundation
- The proposed United Nation's population center (UNPC) (Reports 006275), 1970 (Box 281)
  International Division/Population Program
  13 p.
  Birth control -- India; Population research -- India; Cool, John C., 1926-; Ford Foundation. Population Program
- Analysis of monthly consumer off-take of Nirodh in Andhra Pradesh: current levels and maximum gain expected as a result of extensive consumer sampling, 1970. (Reports 006276) (Box 281)
  Chart of consumer activity from April-July 1970 in Andhra Pradesh.
  International Division;India, Nepal and Sri Lanka
  Consumption (Economics) -- India -- Andhra Pradesh
- New alignments in the Ministry of Health and Family Planning (Reports 006277), 1970 (Box 281)
  Issue of a newsletter published by Ford Foundation, New Delhi. Articles include Modifications in the classical diffusion model for family planning, by Everett M. Rogers, Population studies centers in India: a brief note, and Direct mailing for family plan
  International Division/Middle East and Africa;India, Nepal and Sri Lanka
  Ford Foundation Series
  Program letter: Family planning
  Birth control -- India; Communication in birth control -- India; Ford Foundation. Field Office New Delhi; Ford Foundation. Middle East and Africa
- Report on the operations of aid to Pakistan from the Ford Foundation (Reports 006278), 1957 (Box 281)
  A review of economic aid to Pakistan from the Ford Foundation.
  Overseas Division;India, Nepal and Sri Lanka
  v, 18 p.: tables
  Economic assistance -- Pakistan; Charity organization -- Pakistan; Philanthropy -- Pakistan; Pakistan. Ministry of Economic Affairs.; Ford Foundation. Overseas Development Program
- Communication Action Research Project: A study in family planning communication, Meerut District (Reports 006279), 1966 (Box 281)
  Review of a low-keyed family planning information program in Meerut District. Program designed to improve communication and to set up a system of distribution of condoms at subsidized rates.
  International Division/South and Southeast Asia;India, Nepal and Sri Lanka
  65 p. + appendices: ill., tables, forms
  Communication in birth control -- India -- Meerut (District); Birth control -- India -- Meerut (District); Birth control research -- India -- Meerut (District); Contraception -- India -- Meerut (District); Contraceptives -- India -- Meerut (District); Raina, B. L. (Bishen Lal), 1911-; Blake, Robert R. (Robert Rogers), 1918-2004; Wiss, Eugene M.; National Institute of Family Planning (India); National Institute of Family Planning (India)
- Poverty in poor nations (Reports 006280), 1966 (Box 282)
  Excerpt from Transactions of the Sixth World Congress of Sociology, volume II (1967), (pp. [173]-1850.
  International Division/National Affairs
  [13 p.]
  Related Conference
  World Congress of Sociology (6th: 1966: Evian-les-Bains, France)
  Poverty -- Social aspects; Sociology -- Congresses; Social sciences -- Congresses; Miller, S. M. (Seymour Michael), 1922-; International Sociological Association
- The Communication Centre (Reports 006281), 1970 (Box 282)
  The Communication Centre was created to deal with a whole range of communication problems associated with agricultural development.
  8 p.: ports.
  Communication in agriculture -- India; Agriculture -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- India; Agricultural development projects -- India; Uttar Pradesh Agricultural University; Uttar Pradesh Agricultural University
- Women's coordination committee (Reports 006282), 1975 (Box 282)
  Staff memo dated December 19, 1975.
  Office of the President
  Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations -- United States -- Administration; Women -- Services for -- United States; Women's rights -- United States; Bundy, McGeorge; Ford Foundation. Office of the President; Ford Foundation. Coordinating Committee on Women's Programs
- Curriculum development: a case study in Kenya (Reports 006283), 1967 (Box 282)
  26 p. + appendices
  Curriculum planning -- Kenya -- Case studies; Education -- Kenya -- Curricula; Education -- Kenya -- Equipment and supplies; Teachers colleges -- Kenya; Teachers -- Training of -- Kenya; Education and state -- Kenya; Oluoch, G. P. (Gilbert Paul); Warren, William S., Jr.
- An international (Mexican) version of the Academic Administration Internship Program (Reports 006284), 1967 (Box 282)
  14 p.
  Internship programs -- Mexico; Educational exchanges -- Mexico; Teacher exchange programs -- Mexico; Teacher exchange programs -- Latin America; Educational exchanges -- Latin America; Universities and colleges -- Mexico -- Administration; Education, Higher; Keegan, Frank L.; Ford Foundation. Latin America and the Caribbean
- The U.S. professor in Latin America: His cold war and other problems (Reports 006285), 1966 (Box 282)
  12 p.
  Education, Higher -- Political aspects -- Latin America; Teacher exchange programs -- Latin America; Educational exchanges -- Latin America; Social sciences -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- Latin America; Keegan, Frank L.; Ford Foundation. Latin America and the Caribbean
- Terminal report from local consultants in educational administration (Reports 006286), 1972 (Box 282)
  Universities and colleges -- Philippines -- Administration; Education (Graduate) -- Philippines -- Administration; Falcone, M. Baldomero; Ordenez, Victor M.; Ford Foundation. Asia and the Pacific
- Reflections on the planning of expanded rice exports (Reports 006287), 1968 (Box 282)
  59 p. + appendices: tables
  Rice trade -- Pakistan; Rice -- Research -- Pakistan; Agricultural productivity -- Pakistan; Agriculture -- Economic aspects -- Pakistan; Aresvik, Oddvar, 1915-; Ford Foundation. Asia and the Pacific
- Comments on J. Wallace Madill report: wheat marketing in Pakistan: an appraisal of prospects and requirements (Reports 006288), 1969 (Box 282)
  Title sufficient as abstract.
  24 p.: tables
  Wheat trade -- Pakistan; Grain trade -- Pakistan; Agricultural productivity -- Pakistan; Agriculture -- Economic aspects -- Pakistan; Aresvik, Oddvar, 1915-; Madill, J. Wallace; Narvaez Morales, Ignacio; Borlaug, Norman E. (Norman Ernest), 1914-2009; Ford Foundation. Asia and the Pacific
- Report on trip June-August 1965 to Bangkok, Singapore, Hong Kong, Tokyo, London, Amsterdam, Brussels, Paris, Marseilles, Geneva, Athens (Reports 006289) (Box 282)
  Report on observations on urbanization in other countries to see what could be applied to the author's work with the Calcutta Metropolitan Planning Organization.
  International Division/South and Southeast Asia
  22 p.
  Urbanization; Urbanization -- India -- Calcutta (India); City planning -- India; Andrade, C. Preston, 1912-1978; Ford Foundation. South and Southeast Asia
- Report of a trip to study the possibilities for upland rice improvement in Brazil (Reports 006290), 1975 (Box 282)
  6 p.
  Rice -- Research -- Brazil; Rice trade -- Brazil; Agriculture -- Research -- Brazil; Agricultural productivity -- Brazil; Agronomy -- Brazil; Agricultural assistance -- Brazil; Sánchez, Pedro A., 1940-; Ford Foundation. Latin America and the Caribbean
- Central Institute of Indian Languages (Reports 006291), 1974 (Box 282)
  Overview of the Central Institute of Indian Languages and the activities in which it engages.
  Language and languages -- Study and teaching -- India; Quinn, John A.; Central Institute of Indian Languages
- Preliminary report on Japan (Reports 006292), 1953 (Box 282)
  Prepared for the Working Party of the Ford Foundation" --T.p.
  Overseas Division
  31 p.: tables, 28 cm.
  Charity organization -- Japan; Endowments -- Japan -- Evaluation; Philanthropy -- Japan; Condliffe, J. B. (John Bell), 1891-1981; Ford Foundation
- Foundation activities related to Japan (Reports 006293), 1953 (Box 282)
  Report prepared for the Working Party of the Ford Foundation. --T.p.
  [12] p.
  Charity organization -- Japan; Condliffe, J. B. (John Bell), 1891-1981; Ford Foundation; Ford Foundation. Overseas Development Program
- Report on Iraq (Reports 006294), 1954 (Box 282)
  4 p.
  Technical assistance -- Middle East; Allen, H. B.; Ford Foundation. Overseas Development Program
- Visit to the University of London, Institute of Education, February 6-7 (Reports 006295), 1975 (Box 282)
  File memo dated February 27, 1975.
  Education (Graduate) -- England; Educational exchanges -- Latin America; Educational exchanges -- England; Student exchange programs -- Latin America; Student exchange programs -- England; Myers, Robert G.; Ford Foundation. Latin America and the Caribbean; University of London. Institute of Education
- Visit to Institute of Development Studies (Reports 006296), 1975 (Box 282)
  File memo dated February 14, 1975.
  6 p. -- 28 cm.
  Economics -- Research -- Latin America; Myers, Robert G.; Institute of Development Studies (Brighton, England)
- Visit to the Centre for the Economics of Education of the London School of Economics - Febaurary 7, 1975 (Reports 006297) (Box 282)
  File memo datedFebruary 27, 1975.
  2 p. + attachement -- 28 cm.
  Economics -- Study and teaching (Graduate); Economists -- Training of; Myers, Robert G.; Ford Foundation. Latin America and the Caribbean
- Conference on population socialization, East-West Population Institute (Reports 006298), 1974 (Box 282)
  File memo dated January 7, 1975.
  6 p.: ill.
  Population -- Social aspects -- Congresses; Communication in birth control -- Developing countries -- Congresses; Fertility, Human -- Social aspects -- Developing countries; Family size -- Developing countries; Sex role -- Developing countries; Social learning; Germain, Adrienne; East-West Population Institute; Ford Foundation. Population Program
- UNEP report (Reports 006299), 1974 (Box 282)
  26 p.: ill., chart, tables
  Human ecology -- Developing countries; Human settlements -- Developing countries; Environmental management -- Developing countries; Environmental policy -- Developing countries; Technology transfer -- Developing countries; Technical assistance -- Developing countries; Ames, Edward A.; Ruff, Larry E. (Larry Edward), 1941-; United Nations Environment Programme; Ford Foundation
- Report on West Bengal on family planning in India for May 1969 (Reports 006300) (Box 282)
  Memo to Douglas Ensminger dated June 2, 1969.
  International Division/Population Program;India, Nepal and Sri Lanka
  Birth control -- India; Contraception -- India; Mosley, Kirk T.; Ford Foundation. Population Program
- Analysis of alternative agricultural strategies in the South of Chile (Reports 006301), 1970 (Box 282)
  Agriculture -- Economic aspects -- Chile; Farm management -- Chile; Agricultural productivity -- Chile; Daines, Samuel R.
- Some observations on the survival of children around the world (Reports 006302), 1974 (Box 282)
  International Division/Board of Trustees
  Children -- Research -- Developing countries; Children -- Social conditions -- Developing countries; Children -- Health and hygiene -- Developing countries; Children -- Education -- Developing countries; Children's rights -- Developing countries; Wald, Patricia M.
- The national program of family planning in Indonesia (Reports 006303), 1968 (Box 282)
  "Prepared by the Ad Hoc Committee, July 1968, for presentation to GAPPENAS." --T.p.
  6 p. + attachment: tables
  Birth control -- Indonesia; Population assistance -- Indonesia; Ford Foundation. Asia and the Pacific
- Dr. Gary W. Carrivear, Ford Foundation consultant in Thailand 26 May through 27 (Reports 006304), 1974 (Box 282)
  Archaeometry -- Study and teaching -- Thailand; Archaeology -- Research -- Thailand; Archaeology -- Methodology -- Study and teaching; Archaeology -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- Thailand; Carrivear, Gary W.; Ford Foundation. Asia and the Pacific
- Summary of work completed on research and excavation at Ban Chiang (Reports 006305), 1974 (Box 282)
  3 p.
  Archaeology -- Research -- Thailand; Excavations (Archaeology) -- Thailand -- Ban Chiang (Udon Thani); Archaeology -- Thailand; Archaeometry -- Thailand; Pietrusewsky, Michael; Ford Foundation. Asia and the Pacific
- Equality of educational opportunity: a study of primary schooling in Thailand (Reports 006306), 1974 (Box 282)
  "... Interim report of a study conducted by the National Education Commission, Ministry of Education, and the Division of Rural Elementary Education, Department of Local Administration, Ministry of Interior, [Thailand]" --T.p.
  78 p. + attachments: tables
  Education, Elementary -- Research -- Thailand; Education, Rural -- Research -- Thailand; Education -- Social aspects -- Thailand; Educational equalization -- Thailand; Right to education -- Thailand; Education and state -- Thailand; Fuller, William P.; Ford Foundation. Asia and the Pacific; Thailand. Krasūang Mahātthai
- Report to the government of Bangladesh by CIMMYT consultants (Reports 006307), 1974 (Box 282)
  26 p. + appendix
  Agriculture -- Research -- Pakistan; Wheat -- Research -- Pakistan; Anderson, R. G. (Robert Glenn), 1924-1981; Saari, E. E. (Eugene Eino); Ford Foundation. Asia and the Pacific
- Draft of recommendations on an exchange of persons program for Ford Foundation purposes for 1952 (Reports 006308), 1951 (Box 282)
  International Affairs
  22 p. + appendices: tables
  Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations -- United States -- Management; Endowments -- Evaluation; Charity organization; Ford Foundation Program development; Ford Foundation Management
- Summary of survey of research activities in Burma (Reports 006309), 1954 (Box 282)
  Education, Higher -- Burma -- Curricula; College teachers -- Training of -- Burma; Higher education and state -- Burma; Education and state -- Burma; Biology -- Research -- Burma; Technology -- Research -- Burma; Economics -- Research -- Burma; History -- Research; Everton, John Scott
- Rationale of the educational programme of the third plan (Reports 006310), 1964 (Box 282)
  Overseas Division/South and Southeast Asia
  46 p. + appendices: tables
  Education and state -- Pakistan; Education, Elementary -- Pakistan; Education, Higher -- Pakistan; Education -- Economic aspects -- Pakistan; Educational planning -- Pakistan; School enrollment -- Pakistan; Universities and colleges -- Pakistan; Technical education; Curle, Adam; Ford Foundation. Overseas Development. South and Southeast Asia
- Foundations in Latin America (Reports 006311), 1952 (Box 282)
  Overseas Division/Latin America and the Caribbean
  3, 6 p. + attachment
  Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations -- Latin America; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations -- Bibliography; Charity organization -- Latin America; Ford Foundation. Overseas Development Program
- Guides for technical assistance to less-developed countries: an appraisal plan (Reports 006312), 1952 (Box 282)
  Overseas Training and Research
  16 p.: table
  Technical assistance -- Developing countries; Charity organization -- Developing countries; Sociology, Rural -- Developing countries; International cooperation; Nelson, Lowry, 1893-
- FY 1973 budget (Reports 006313), 1972 (Box 282)
  Memo to McGeorge Bundy dated February 23, 1972.
  Public Broadcasting
  4 p.: table
  Public broadcasting -- United States -- Finance; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations -- United States -- Finance; Endowments -- United States -- Evaluation; Friendly, Fred W.; Ford Foundation. Public Broadcasting; Ford Foundation
- Description of the Venezuela program (Reports 006314), 1965 (Box 283)
  various pagings: tables
  Venezuela -- Politics and government; Venezuela -- Economic policy; Ford Foundation; Ford Foundation. Overseas Development. Latin America and the Caribbean
- Children and television seminar (Reports 006315), 1973 (Box 283)
  Collection of papers on television and the social implications of television advertising on children.
  1 v. (various pagings) -- 28 cm.